A Guide to the Frederick J. McCoy Papers, 1971-1991 (bulk 1971-1980)
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Frederick J. McCoy Papers, 1971-1991 (bulk 1971-1980)
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 06-83
0.5 linear feet
The Frederick J. McCoy Papers consists of 0.5 linear feet and spans the years 19701-1991. The collection consists of correspondence, photocopies of newspaper articles, photographs, campaign materials, news releases, reports, meeting agendas, a legal brief, an autographed book, and other materials collected by Fred McCoy related to the City of Fairfax, primarily during his tenure on the City Council from 1972 to 1978.
McCoy, Frederick (Fred) J.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Donated by Dee Schmidt and Fred J. McCoy in 2013
Historical and Biographical Information
Frederick (Fred) J. McCoy grew up in Queens, New York, and graduated from Andrew Jackson High School in New York City in 1947. After graduating from high school, he worked as a machinist from 1947 to 1949, and then as a purchasing agent from 1949 to 1951. He served in the U.S. Army from 1951 to 1953, after being honorably discharged, returned to work as a purchasing agent from 1953 to 1958. McCoy attended the Pratt Institute (1948-1951) and Long Island University (1954-1958) and graduated from Georgetown University School of Dentistry with his Doctor of Dental Surgery degree in 1962. Upon graduation, he moved to the City of Fairfax and opened a dental practice based in his home that he ran until retiring in 2006.
McCoy was elected to the City of Fairfax City Council for the 1972-1974, 1974-1976, and 1976-1978 terms. During the 1972 and 1974 elections, McCoy was elected as part of the “Fairfax Citizens for a Livable City” slate of candidates, who promoted balancing commercial development with preserving the residential character of the city and encouraged citizen participation in the government. Critical issues during the 1976 election included bond referendums for $1.75 million in capital improvements at two city elementary schools as well as city transportation and a gas tax to pay for Northern Virginia’s Metro bus costs. McCoy opposed paying the full Metro deficit, believing it outweighed the service and benefits the city received. He also opposed the school bonds as being “extravagant” and potentially requiring a raise in taxes. McCoy was defeated in his bid for reelection in 1978. A critical issue during the 1978 election was whether the city would maintain a contract with Fairfax County to remain within the county school system or establish a separate city school system. All of the candidates who supported an independent school system, including McCoy, were defeated. During his time on the City Council, McCoy served on the Council of Governments Transportation Planning Board, the Committee on Drug Abuse, and the Storm Drainage Committee. McCoy unsuccessfully ran for mayor in 1980 with a campaign theme of “Let’s Talk City!” focused on open and transparent government and informed citizens.
Scope and Content
The Frederick J. McCoy Papers consists of 0.5 linear feet and spans the years 1971-1991. The collection consists of correspondence, photocopies of newspaper articles, photographs, campaign materials, news releases, reports, meeting agendas, a legal brief, an autographed book, and other materials collected by Fred McCoy related to the City of Fairfax, primarily during his tenure on the City Council from 1972 to 1978. Subjects covered are City of Fairfax issues and elections and the City of Fairfax City Council.
His papers include photocopies of newspaper articles originally printed between June 1972 and January 1978 and in January 1991 about political, social, economic, and planning related topics involving the City of Fairfax and its residents. Also included are working papers of the City Council, including correspondence with the City Manager, the City’s Comprehensive Development Plan, and reports from commissioned planning studies and analyses such as a storm drainage analysis and a revenues-expenditures analysis. Also included are City Council and Mayor campaign materials, primarily from the 1974, 1976, 1978, and 1980 elections; city news releases; photographs; Fred McCoy’s correspondence; invitations and programs for the city’s swearing in ceremonies; school board meeting agendas, bond referendums, and newsletter articles related to city schools; Brief of Appellee for Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, et al., v. City of Fairfax, Virginia; the Northern Virginia Sun’s Volume IV of the “Editor’s Viewpoint” columns; a book entitled “The Rating Game” published by The Twentieth Century Fund and signed by author John E. Petersen; and an official statement of the city’s transit bonds offered in October 1972. Also included is a tabletop placard for Fairfax City Express fare cards for express commuter bus service to Washington, D.C., and the Pentagon.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
None
Index Terms
Elections - Virginia - City of Fairfax; City of Fairfax City Council (Fairfax, Va.); McCoy, Frederick J.
Container List
- Brief of Appellee, Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, et al., v. City of Fairfax, Virginia, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- City Council Papers, 1971 May-1978 February (Box 1, Folder 2)
- City News Releases, 1972 October-1973 October (Box 1, Folder 3)
- City Schools Information, 1976 March-1976 May; 1978 January (Box 1, Folder 4)
- City Swearing in Ceremonies Invitations and Programs, 1972 June, 1974 June, 1976 June (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1972 April-1980 April (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Mayor and City Council Campaign Materials, 1972 March-1988 March (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Newspaper Clippings, June 1972-January 1978 [Photocopies], Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Newspaper Clippings, July 1972-December 1976, July 1991 [Photocopies], Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Northern Virginia Sun, Editor’s Viewpoint, Vol. IV, September 1974-August 1975, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Photographs, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- The Rating Game, The Twentieth Century Fund, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Transit Bonds Official Statement, 1972 October (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Fairfax City Express Fare Card Advertisement, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)